<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEXT SYSTEM "file:./xml2html/data/xml/DOCUMENT.dtd">

<TEXT>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Getting Access to the Source Code">

<P>
<MACRO NAME="madmpi"/> files are hosted by the project PM2 on the
InriaGforge at <URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/projects/pm2/</URL>.

The source code is managed by a <TT>Subversion</TT> server hosted by
the InriaGforge. To get the source code, you need:
</P>

<OL>
<LI>
<P>
To install the client side of the software <TT>Subversion</TT> if it
is not already available on your system. The software can be obtained
from <URL>http://subversion.tigris.org/</URL>.
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
To become a member of the project <TT>pm2</TT>. For this, you first
need to get an account to the gForge server. You can then become a
member of the project by contacting one of the project administrators.
The list of the project administrators is available from the main
project page.
</P>
<P>
You can also choose to check out the project's SVN repository through
anonymous access. In that case, you do not need to become a member,
and you will have limited access to the repository.
</P>
</LI>
</OL>

<P>
More information on how to get a gForge account, to become a member of
the specified project, or on any other related task can be obtained
from the InriaGforge at <URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/</URL>. The most
important thing is to upload your public SSH key on the gForge server
(see the FAQ at
<URL>http://siteadmin.gforge.inria.fr/FAQ.html#Q6</URL> for
instructions).
</P>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Required Development Tools" LABEL="sec:tools">

<P>
The following development tools are required to compile <MACRO
NAME="madmpi"/>:
</P>

<UL>
<LI>
<P>
GNU C Compiler <TT>gcc</TT> (version <TT>3.2</TT> and higher).
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
GNU <TT>make</TT> (version <TT>3.81</TT> and higher).
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
GNU Bison (<URL>http://www.gnu.org/software/bison/</URL>) and Flex (<URL>http://www.gnu.org/software/flex/</URL>).
</P>
</LI>
</UL>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Prerequisites">

<P>
To use Myrinet and Quadrics, you must get the appropriate drivers.
<MACRO NAME="madmpi"/> supports Myrinet networks through the MX driver
and Quadrics networks through the ELAN driver.
</P>

<IGNORE>
<P>
The default installation directories for these drivers are:
</P>

<UL>
<LI> <TT>/opt/mx</TT> for Myrinet/MX; </LI>
<LI> <TT>/opt/DIS</TT> for SCI/SISCI. </LI>
</UL>

<P>
In case, your installation differs from these directories, you will
need to set the following environment variables to point to your own
installation directories:
</P>
</IGNORE>

<CODE FILE="./code/setDrivers.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Installing PM2">

<P>
Here are the required steps to install PM2.
</P>

<OL>
<LI>
<P>
Choose an installation directory for PM2, and set the environment
variable <TT>PM2_ROOT</TT> to this directory.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./code/setenvPm2.txt"/>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
Go in the parent directory of the directory <TT>PM2_ROOT</TT> and
check out the latest version from the <TT>Subversion</TT> server
</P>
  <UL>
  <LI>
  <P>
  using the anonymous access.
  </P>
  <CODE FILE="./code/svnPm2anon.txt"/>
  </LI>
  <LI>
  <P>
  or using your gForge account.
  </P>
  <CODE FILE="./code/svnPm2.txt"/>
  </LI>
  </UL>

<P>
You should end up with a directory named <TT>pm2</TT>.
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
You need to add to your <TT>PATH</TT> the directory <TT>pm2/bin</TT>.
</P>

<CODE FILE="./code/setPath.txt"/>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
PM2 is installed.
</P>
</LI>
</OL>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Installing Mad-MPI" LABEL="installMadMpi">

<P>
Here are the required steps to install <MACRO NAME="madmpi"/>.
</P>

<OL>
<LI>
<P>
Create the PM2 flavor tuned for <MACRO NAME="madmpi"/>.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./code/createFlavor.txt"/>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
Compile <MACRO NAME="madmpi"/>.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./code/compileMadMpi.txt"/>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
You need to provide a network configuration file, located in
<TT>${PM2_ROOT}/nmad/examples/mpi/networks.cfg</TT>. This file is
mandatory but users can select another location by defining the
appropriate environment variable (see Section <REF
LABEL="advanced"/>). When loading a <MACRO NAME="madmpi"/>
application, the network configuration file is read to determine which
network links to use between the different machines involved in the
execution. The sample file
<TT>$PM2_ROOT/leonie/examples/networks.cfg</TT> can be used as a model
to describe your network configuration.
</P>
</LI>

<LI> 
<P>
Users should add to their <TT>PATH</TT> the element
<TT>nmad/protocols/proto_mpi/scripts/</TT> in order to easily access the
commands <TT>mpicc</TT> and <TT>mpirun</TT>.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./code/setPath2.txt"/>
</LI>
</OL>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Summary of Environment Variables" LABEL="variables">

<P>
Here the list of environment variables you need to set (preferably in
your login files such as <TT>$HOME/.bashrc</TT>) before being able to
compile and execute <MACRO NAME="madmpi"/> applications.
</P>

<CODE FILE="./code/variables.txt"/>
</SUBSECTION>

</TEXT>

