<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEXT SYSTEM "file:../xml2html/data/xml/DOCUMENT.dtd">

<TEXT>

<P>
This section describes how to install PM2 on your own machine.
Please, first check that your system configuration fits the
installation pre-requisites, especially with respect to the GNU
utilities as mentioned in Section <REF LABEL="sec:tools"/>.
</P>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="PM2 pre-requisites">

<P>
PM2 is a highly portable and efficient environment and the current
software is yet available on a wide range of architectures. The
implementation is built on top of several distinct software
components: Marcel and Madeleine. we briefly review the currently
supported architectures and systems.
</P>

<SUBSUBSECTION TITLE="Multithreading: Marcel">

<P>
Marcel is a POSIX-compliant thread package which provides extra
features, such as thread migration.  Marcel is currently available on
the following platforms, listed in the <TT>ARCHITECTURES</TT> file of the
distribution:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/archi.txt"/>

</SUBSUBSECTION>

<SUBSUBSECTION TITLE="Communication: Madeleine">

<P>
Madeleine is a generic communication interface
which is able to fully exploit the low latency and the high bandwidth
of high-speed networks such as Myrinet or SCI. This PM2 communication
subsystem currently supports the following communication interfaces:
TCP, MPI (LAM-MPI, MPI-BIP), VIA, BIP (on top of Myrinet), SISCI (on
top of SCI) and SBP (on top of Fast-Ethernet).
</P>
</SUBSUBSECTION>

<SUBSUBSECTION TITLE="Required development tools" LABEL="sec:tools">

<P>
As previously mentioned, PM2 has been designed to be easily portable
and only relies on the availability of the two following development
tools:
</P>

<UL>
<LI>
<P>
GNU C Compiler <TT>gcc</TT> (version <TT>3.2</TT> and higher). The
version <TT>2.95</TT> of <TT>gcc</TT> can also be used, but you need
to uncomment the last line in the <TT>pm2/make/config</TT>.
</P>
</LI>
<LI>
<P>
GNU <TT>make</TT> (version <TT>3.81</TT> and higher).
</P>
</LI>
</UL>

<P>
Also, PM2 includes a large number of shell scripts, which are assumed
to be run with the <EM>GNU utilities</EM> such
as <TT>expr</TT>, <TT>tr</TT>, <TT>head</TT>, <TT>cut</TT>, <TT>test</TT>.
A shell that understands substitutions
like <TT>${var/find/replace}</TT>, for
instance <TT>bash</TT>, <TT>zsh</TT>, <TT>ksh</TT>, is needed to run
these scripts.
</P>

</SUBSUBSECTION>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Getting the PM2 software and help">

<P>
PM2 files are hosted on the InriaGforge server at
<URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/projects/pm2/</URL>, also accessible from
the PM2 web site at <URL>http://runtime.bordeaux.inria.fr/pm2/</URL>.
</P>

<P>
Please, send an email to <EMAIL>pm2-users@lists.gforge.inria.fr</EMAIL> if you encounter
problems with the PM2 software. However, please first make sure that
your problem is not already listed in the <EM>Frequently Asked
  Questions</EM> Section <REF LABEL="sec:faq"/>.
</P>

<SUBSUBSECTION TITLE="Getting the latest release">

<P>
The latest release for the package <TT>pm2</TT> is available from the
main page of the project PM2 at
<URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/projects/pm2/</URL> under the tab
<B>Files</B>. It can be extracted with the following command
entered at the shell prompt:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2extract.txt"/>

</SUBSUBSECTION>

<SUBSUBSECTION TITLE="Getting the latest version">

<P>
The source code is
managed by a <TT>Subversion</TT> server hosted by the InriaGforge. To
get the source code, you need:
</P>

<OL>
<LI>
<P>
To install the client side of the software <TT>Subversion</TT> if it
is not already available on your system. The software can be obtained
from <URL>http://subversion.tigris.org/</URL>.
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
To become a member of the project <TT>pm2</TT>. For this, you first
need to get an account to the gForge server. You can then send a
request to join the <TT>pm2</TT> project
(<URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/project/request.php?group_id=30</URL>).
</P>
<P>
You can also choose to check out the project's SVN repository through
anonymous access. In that case, you do not need to become a member,
and you will have limited access to the repository.
</P>
</LI>
</OL>

<P>
More information on how to get a gForge account, to become a member of
a project, or on any other related task can be obtained from the
InriaGforge at <URL>https://gforge.inria.fr/</URL>. The most important
thing is to upload your public SSH key on the gForge server (see the
FAQ at <URL>http://siteadmin.gforge.inria.fr/FAQ.html#Q6</URL> for
instructions).
</P>

<P>
You can now check out the latest version from the <TT>Subversion</TT>
server
</P>
<UL>
<LI>
<P>
using the anonymous access.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./Progs/svnPm2anon.txt"/>
</LI>
<LI>
<P>
or using your gForge account.
</P>
<CODE FILE="./Progs/svnPm2.txt"/>
</LI>
</UL>

</SUBSUBSECTION>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="The PM2 distribution">


<P>
Once extracted, the PM2 distribution should be available under the
<TT>./pm2/</TT> directory. The PM2 distribution is organized as follows:
</P>

<DL>
<DT><TT>appli</TT> </DT>       <DD>Application configuration</DD>
<DT><TT>bin</TT> </DT>         <DD>PM2 scripts</DD>
<DT><TT>common</TT> </DT>      <DD>Common configuration scripts to all modules</DD>
<DT><TT>doc</TT> </DT>         <DD>Documentation files</DD>
<DT><TT>ezflavor</TT> </DT>    <DD>Flavor configuration graphic interface</DD>
<DT><TT>generic</TT> </DT>     <DD>Common configuration options</DD>
<DT><TT>init</TT> </DT>        <DD></DD>
<DT><TT>leonie</TT> </DT>      <DD>Bootstrap code for PM2 applications</DD>
<DT><TT>leoparse</TT> </DT>    <DD>Parser for PM2 configuration files</DD>
<DT><TT>mad3</TT> </DT>        <DD>Communication subsystem (obsolete version)</DD>
<DT><TT>make</TT> </DT>        <DD>PM2 makefile system</DD>
<DT><TT>marcel</TT> </DT>      <DD>Multithreading subsystem</DD>
<DT><TT>memory</TT> </DT>      <DD>Memory management system</DD>
<DT><TT>modules</TT> </DT>     <DD>Link to all the PM2 modules</DD>
<DT><TT>nmad</TT> </DT>        <DD>Communication subsystem (current version)</DD>
<DT><TT>ntbx</TT> </DT>        <DD>Generic network management utility toolbox</DD>
<DT><TT>pioman</TT> </DT>      <DD>Generic I/O manager</DD>
<DT><TT>pm2</TT> </DT>         <DD>PM2 <EM>en personne</EM>! </DD>
<DT><TT>profile</TT> </DT>     <DD>PM2 profiling utilities</DD>
<DT><TT>puk</TT></DT>          <DD>Padico micro-kernel</DD>
<DT><TT>stackalign</TT> </DT>  <DD>Stack initialization for Marcel</DD>
<DT><TT>tbx</TT> </DT>         <DD>Generic PM2 utility toolbox </DD>
</DL>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Setting the environment variables">

<P>
Several environment variables have to be set so that PM2 correctly
works.
</P>

<UL>

<LI>
<P>
The <TT>PM2_ROOT</TT> variable contains the path to the PM2
distribution root directory. Setting that variable is
<B>mandatory</B>. It is the only one needed, all other variables have
default values.

<IGNORE>
Observe that PM2 does not write
anything into this directory: a write-protected directory is OK.
</IGNORE>
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
It is highly recommended to add the directory <TT>${PM2_ROOT}/bin</TT>
in the active search path.
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
The <TT>PM2_HOME</TT> variable contains the path to the PM2
administrative directory. The default is your home directory
<TT>${HOME}</TT>.
</P>
</LI>

<LI>
<P>
By default, configuration files are stored in the
<TT>${PM2_HOME}/.pm2</TT> directory. You can change this by setting
the <TT>PM2_CONF_DIR</TT> variable to another directory.
</P>
<P>
All the files generated within the compilation process will be placed
by default in the <TT>${PM2_ROOT}/build</TT> directory, more precisely
in the <TT>${PM2_ROOT}/build/${PM2_ASM}</TT>. The environment variable
<TT>PM2_ASM</TT> describes the architecture of the machine and is set
to the result of the call <TT>pm2-arch --pm2-asm</TT>. If you wish to
keep the compiled files into another directory, you can set the
<TT>PM2_BUILD_DIR</TT> environment variable to this directory. The
files will then be kept in the <TT>${PM2_BUILD_DIR}/${PM2_ASM}</TT>
directory.
</P>
<P>
Please note that these two directories have to be reachable from any
machine used when running PM2 programs. Using the <TT>/tmp</TT>
directory would not be suitable!
</P>
</LI>
</UL>

<P>
You may wish to insert the following lines in your <TT>.cshrc</TT> file (if
your default shell is <TT>csh</TT>):
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/settingVariables.txt"/>

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Please make sure that these variables are correctly set within
  remote shell commands (i.e., scripts invoked by <TT>ssh</TT>).
  </EM>
</WARNING>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Creating the standard PM2 flavors" LABEL="subsec:compiling">

<P>
You should now create your own, private configuration database. The
files are stored in the <TT>${PM2_HOME}/.pm2</TT> directory, and
consist of a set of <EM>flavors</EM>. A flavor is simply a (rather
complex!) set of options to be passed to the PM2 modules at
compilation time and/or at execution time. Flavors are organized so as
to let you easily maintain several versions of the PM2 system at the
same time: for instance, one version for the TCP protocol and another
version for the BIP/Myrinet protocol. Or, one version with the
debugging parameters on, and another one with the debugging parameters
turned off for performance.
</P>

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Do not forget to re-source your <TT>.cshrc</TT> file to activate the new
  environment variables and the new search <TT>PATH</TT>.
  </EM>
</WARNING>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeInit.txt"/>

<P>
This checks the whole source hierarchy for consistency, and extracts the
option sets for each PM2 module if necessary. It then creates
the various flavors. You can list them by calling
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/flavorList.txt"/>

<IGNORE>
<P>
In the following, we advise you to use the <TT>pm2</TT> standard
flavor. Just have a look at it to get a feeling of its different parameters.
You will probably never dare to do it again!
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/flavorGet.txt"/>

<P>
The <TT>pm2-flavor</TT> command offers several other functionalities. See
<TT>pm2-flavor -h</TT> for the extensive on-line help.
</P>
</IGNORE>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Selecting your own PM2 flavor" LABEL="subsec:configuring">

<P>
Configuring PM2 is quite straightforward. The underlying platform is
automatically detected. Hence, there is no need to specify the
operating system/processor pair.
</P>

<P>
Configuring flavors is done through a set of external utilities to be
introduced later. We strongly discourage you to edit the flavor files
by hand.
</P>

<P>
In the following, we will use different flavors of PM2 depending on
which aspect of PM2 we wish to use. Selecting a flavor is done by
setting the environment variable <TT>PM2_FLAVOR</TT> to the name of
the flavor one wishes to use.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setPm2Flavor.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<IGNORE>
<SUBSECTION TITLE="Compiling the library">

<P>
You are now ready for the big step: compiling the whole library.

<IGNORE>
No files are created in the <TT>${PM2_ROOT}</TT> directory, so that
you can compile and install PM2 from a CDROM.
</IGNORE>

All the files will be created in the <TT>${PM2_BUILD_DIR}</TT>
directory.
</P>

<WARNING>
  <EM>
Remember that this directory
must be accessible from all machines included in the PM2
configuration. A local <TT>/tmp</TT> directory will not work!
  </EM>
</WARNING>

<P>
To launch the whole compilation, just invoke <TT>make</TT> from the
<TT>$PM2_ROOT</TT> directory.
</P>

<WARNING>
  <EM>
Make sure you
use the <EM>right</EM> version of the program (see above for detailed
specification). Only recent GNU versions will work!
  </EM>
</WARNING>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/make.txt"/>

<P>
You may wish to follow precisely the compilation process, to do so,
set the <TT>VERB</TT> variable of the makefile process to
<TT>verbose</TT>.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeVerbose.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Cleaning out everything">

<P>
The directory tree of the PM2 distribution may be cleaned at any time
from compiled objects and libraries using the command <TT>pm2_clean</TT>.
This may be needed to free some disk space when PM2 is not in use or
to force the whole PM2 distribution to be completely recreated by a
subsequent <TT>make</TT> call.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeClean.txt"/>

<P>
This will clean all the files generated by the compilation process of
the current flavor, i.e the directory
<TT>${PM2_BUILD_DIR}/${PM2_FLAVOR}</TT>. Note that this does not
affect your own <TT>.pm2</TT> flavor directory; if wanted, it has to
be removed by hand.
</P>

</SUBSECTION>
</IGNORE>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Specifying the configuration for execution">

<P>
Before executing a PM2 application, it is needed to specify the list
of host names on which the application is going to run. For this,
use the <TT>pm2-conf</TT> command. Here I want to use my local machine
called <TT>ravel</TT>, and two neighboring ones called
<TT>debussy</TT> and <TT>faure</TT>.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2conf.txt"/>

<P>
Note that a configuration is specific to a specific flavor. Using a
new flavor will require the setting of a configuration for this
flavor.
</P>

<P>
PM2 will consider that processing node<SPACE/>0 is a process run by
<TT>ravel</TT>, node<SPACE/>1 by <TT>debussy</TT> and node<SPACE/>2 by
<TT>faure</TT>.  Observe that I select my current workstation as
node<SPACE/>0. This is for convenience only as PM2 does not require to
be executed on the local machine. Indeed, there is no reason why the
local machine should get enrolled in the execution of the program. When
running a PM2 on a dedicated cluster, the local machine is most
preferably outside the configuration.
</P>

<WARNING>
  <P>
  <EM>
  Just to avoid disturbing problems in the following, please make sure
  that you local machine is allowed to issue <TT>ssh</TT> commands to each
  machine in the configuration, and that the directory <TT>${PM2_ROOT}</TT>
  is actually shared by all of them. You can for example try the following command:
  </EM>
  </P>

  <PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2all.txt"/>

  <P>
  <EM>
  (Note the <TT>'</TT> characters!)
  </EM>
  </P>

  <P>
  <EM>
  This script issues a <TT>ssh</TT> command to each node in the current
  configuration. In case you do not get the list of the files in your
  current <TT>${PM2_ROOT}</TT> directory, but get instead nothing or a
  message similar to <TT>permission denied</TT>, you should then check
  you can connect to the machines which are in your current
  configuration.
  </EM>
  </P>

</WARNING>

<P>
By default, PM2 is connecting to machines using the <TT>ssh</TT>
command. To use another command or to specify parameters for the
<TT>ssh</TT> command, you can set the <TT>PM2_RSH</TT> variable.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2rsh.txt"/>

<IGNORE>
<P>
If <TT>rsh</TT> does not work because of right permissions, a possible
turnaround is to use <TT>ssh</TT> instead of <TT>rsh</TT>:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setPm2Rsh.txt"/>
</IGNORE>

<P>
If you still cannot get a proper output with the command
<TT>pm2-all</TT>, then it could be the remote machines in the
configuration are not correctly served by the network file system. PM2
cannot work, as it implicitly assumes that the executable of the
program will be found on the remote machines at the same place as it
is on the local one.
</P>

<P>
However if it is not possible to correct such problems, it is still
possible to run all three PM2 <EM>virtual nodes</EM> as three processes
on your local machine:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2conflocal.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Creating the Network configuration file" LABEL="sec:network-conf">

<P>
When loading a PM2 program, a network configuration file is read to
determine which network links to use between the different machines
involved in the execution. In our case, we suppose our 3 machines are
connected using the TCP network. The network configuration file can be
created as follows:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/hellonetworks.txt"/>

<P>
You then need to tell PM2 to use your new network configuration file instead of the default one.
This is done by setting the <TT>PM2_LEONIE_NETWORK_FILE</TT> variable.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/sethellonetworks.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION>
<TITLE>Compiling your first <MU/>PM2 program</TITLE>

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Please, make sure that your flavor is actually set to <TT>pm2</TT>:
  </EM>

  <PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setPm2Flavor.txt"/>
</WARNING>

<P>
The PM2 library should now be fully configured.  You are ready to
compile and execute the example programs of the distribution.  Let's
start with the simplest one: <EM>Hello world!</EM>, located in the file
<TT>${PM2_ROOT}/pm2/examples/simple/hello.c</TT>.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeHello.txt"/>

<P>
The compiled version of the program is automatically placed into your
own <TT>build/${PM2_FLAVOR}</TT> directory, but you do need not bother with
this detail at this point: PM2 cares about it for you! Use the
<TT>pm2-which</TT> command to learn where a file is physically located:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/whichHello.txt"/>

<P>
It remains to actually load and run the program.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/pm2load.txt"/>

<P>
You can see that our program generates several times the same message
<TT>Hello world</TT>. Each of the nodes involved in the execution
displays once the message with a call to the <TT>printf</TT> Unix
routine. The output from all the nodes has been redirected to the
console of the starting process.
</P>


<IGNORE>
<P>
You can see that our program generates two messages. The first one is
the expected <EM>Hello World!</EM> message coming from the master
process with a call to the <TT>tprintf</TT> PM2 routine. It is a simple
wrapper of the regular <TT>printf</TT> Unix routine, to be used in
multithreaded context. The second one is some PM2 running statistics
related to the master process. Note that the output of the nodes
different from node<SPACE/>0 does not show up at the terminal. We will see
later how to get them.
</P>
</IGNORE>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Compiling your first Marcel program">

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Please, make sure that your flavor is actually set to <TT>marcel</TT>:
  </EM>

  <PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setMarcelFlavor.txt"/>
</WARNING>

<P>
You can now compile and execute a sample Marcel application.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/checkPm2-2.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Compiling your first Madeleine program">

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Please, make sure that your flavor is actually set to <TT>mad3</TT>:
  </EM>

  <PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setMadFlavor.txt"/>
</WARNING>

<P>
You can now compile and execute a sample Madeleine application.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/checkPm2-3.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Compiling your first NewMadeleine program">

<WARNING>
  <EM>
  Please, make sure that your flavor is actually set to <TT>nmad-mpi</TT>:
  </EM>

  <PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/setNmadFlavor.txt"/>
</WARNING>

<P>
You can now compile and execute a sample NewMadeleine application.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/checkPm2-4.txt"/>

</SUBSECTION>

<SUBSECTION TITLE="Solving problems">

<P>
If something goes wrong at any point, you can always activate the
emergency repair tool provided by PM2.
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeSos.txt"/>

<P>
This results into a listing of your current configuration, attempts to
rebuild the flavor database and clears the compiled PM2 library as
cleanly as possible. It should then restore a fresh and safe
configuration for you, ready to restart the whole compilation. The
output of the command should look like:
</P>

<PROGRAM FILE="./Progs/makeSos2.txt"/>

<P>
Note that the final message is automatically generated!
</P>

</SUBSECTION>

</TEXT>
